thyroid optimization gets a bad rap
because a lot of the time people get put
on T4 monotherapy which is useless or it
can make problems worse the two Feelgood
hormones are testosterone and thyroid
predominantly you know and that those
are the ones that have the greatest
impact on how you feel function perform
and your overall health on a daily basis
are those two those are the
biggies so thyroid is probably the most
controversial one of them all it's the
one that creates IR with the family
physician or internist because it is
poorly understood just like T tone has
been for several decades and I think
what men need to understand out there is
many men out there that get on
testosterone and still have symptoms you
know fatigue brain fog lacal Clarity
weight gain inability to lose weight
even rectile dysfunction things such as
that a lot of times those symptoms are
from thyroid so low acting thyroid in a
man looks just like low acting
testosterone in many areas and that's
why they don't get better when they just
get testosterone in some instances
because the clinic is throwing
testosterone what is actually also a
thyroid problem so that's why you know
but what I found Dave in my practice is
I used to to teach about thyroid right
off the bat about optimizing levels in
men you know understand that thyroid
regulates temperature metabolism
cerebral function and energy levels it
protects you against cardiovascular
disease cognitive impairment fatigue
weight gain memory loss decreases
visceral body fat and improves your
lipid profiles the better the levels
just like with testosterone the better
the benefits so I used to preach to to
the to the men that all the wonderful
benefit of having optimal levels of
thyroid just like having optimal levels
of testosterone they can always
understand testosterone but inevitably
they would call back a month or two
later many of them like why am I taking
this thyroid again I I I don't want to
take anymore I just want to take my
testosterone then they'll stop and
they'll start feeling bad or whatever
and maybe they won't start feeling bad
but the point is then their thyroid labs
are not optimal anymore because that's
what hormon optimization is about is
maintaining optimal levels and so what I
have found that works recently best with
men is men tend to typically do most of
them not all of them some of them
understand hormon optimization after 40
but what I found Dave is that they it
works best in them as far as them
accepting it and understanding it if I
start it after I start testosterone and
the other hormones get everything op
give it time to work and then if they
have symptoms left over still have
persistent fatigue brain fog lack then
they'll start thyroid and they tend to
do much better when they know exactly
the symptoms they're starting it for
versus starting it and optimizing the
levels and not waiting till you get
symptoms of a deficiency so if in a
perfect world if I went back to age 40 I
would start all my hormones whether I
had symptoms or not I would start all my
hormones I maintain I had optimal levels
I would never want I would never want
them to be anything but optimal and uh
that would be and that's Neil rizer's
perfect world too and so that would be
our perfect world but we don't live in
that perfect world so that's kind of my
approach to thyroid it's a vitally
important hormone the two feel-good
hormones are testosterone and thyroid
predominantly you know and that those
are the ones that have the greatest
impact on how you feel function perform
and your overall health on a daily basis
are those two those are the biggies and
so Dave you can tell us how you approach
you know consult the men on on thyroid
but that's kind of the approach that
I've taken after doing that for so long
is I tend to get everything optimal
first and then add thyroid I kind of put
it on deck for them unless they want to
start it off bad they're they're given
the opportunity as every man is just
like with testosterone they can not do
it optimize it from the beginning or
just wait and start it later there's no
wrong answer for that man whatever his
answer is is his answer okay so tell us
how you approach that in in your
practice okay yeah so thyroid is a big
one thyroid is also common in in younger
guys as well again I don't know what it
is sometimes it's Hashimoto which is
autoimmune I think it there's also an
endocrine disruption that plays into
that too military men especially
military men especially bad go ahead the
thing that I've also found is it's
really rampant in the UK maybe it's
something to do with the pollu WEA I
don't know but very rampant over there
so yeah if if you take a list if we
imagine a ven diagram that crosses over
in the middle and you've got low
testosterone symptoms on the side and
you've got thyroid symptoms on one side
they're all in the middle they're the
same they're the same same they are the
same guys you understand that they're
the same they're the same and this idea
that if you're you have to have like
cold extremities to be hypothyroid
that's nonsense true that's nonsense
it's it's I I I believe that that maybe
came from the fact that women run a
little bit lower in temperature than men
so maybe that's the first symptom they
notice but no um they always have to
describe the extremes the extremes are
true hypothyroidism we're not talking
about subclinical hypothyroid or men
with suboptimal thyroid levels we're
talking about those true hypothyroid and
Hyper thyroids so so yeah that's where
that kind of comes from yeah yeah so
when it comes to the thyroid and you've
said this before like when you draw a
line in the sand let's say
hypothetically a free testosterone level
of 50 and and if if you if you're still
wanting to throw more testosterone at it
the chances are there's something else
going on and the chances are if it's
clinical hypogonadism symptoms with
optimal testosterone levels it's thyroid
but that should have already been
checked and taken care of but a lot of
the time it's not when they come to
people like us because it gets
overlooked all the time and they're
afraid of it the afraid of it that's
right that's right they're afraid of it
and they don't know how to do it and
there are so many men walking around
with either undiagnosed hypothyroidism
or damn hypothyroidism and they're on T4
monotherapy T4 monotherapy is like test
gel or pellets um it's crap it's it's
it's almost as good as nothing um the
thing that breaks my heart is when guys
say oh I had my thyroid removed and now
I'm on 100 micrograms of T4 and I'm
obese it's like well you didn't have
much of a chance no so thyroid
optimization gets a bad rap because a
lot of the time people get put on T4
monotherapy which is useless or it can
make problems worse and yes there are
outliers that do great with T4 that's
right but the vast vast vast vast vast
majority of people need T3 and T4 and
natural desiccated thyroid just works
better I used to think and I was wrong
and I will eat my words on this um this
is another one of those you can say I
Told You So moments because 100% true is
T3 T4 if you have the equivalent dose of
NDT a synthetic T3 T4 it doesn't work as
well as the NDT does right um one in 10
people won't tolerate NDT for some weird
reason but the vast majority of people
do ondt I've had be on the equ like
let's say a two grain equivalent dose of
T3 T4 and they swap to NDT and it blows
the levels through the roof like it's
it's a much better medication so yeah
when it comes to thyroid I like to think
of thyroid as putting the wind in the
sales of trt thyroid is responsible for
your metabolism it's your engine I I
talk about thyroid being the furnace
that sits in in in your in your torso
and when thyroid function is low it's
like when people go oh I've just got a
slow metabolis M you've got
hypothyroidism um or when you see those
like I used to know people when I was
young who would just eat everything and
they'd stay stick thin I've recently run
their lab work and they've naturally got
a TSH of like 0.4 and a 3 T3 above the
reference range they're just those out
outliers that's so um you want to have
optimal thyroid function one because
food is wonderful and being able to eat
more nutritious food is wonderful for
you the more good quality emphasis on
good quality the more good quality food
you put into your body the more
nutrients that you can assimilate and
the more powerful of a vessel you can
build it's like basically being a it's
it's like being a more powerful car and
going faster it feels better to be alive
when you've got good thyroid function
when you're low in thyroid Everything
feels like too much effort and the body
constantly has to kick into adrenal
hormones cortisol and adrenaline to get
things done like a dirty backup fuel
source because your body has to kick
into fight or flight just to do basic
day-to-day stuff thyroid is not
amphetamine like you said before thyroid
is not like you're sitting down and
being like Oh I just want to go Take On
The World now but what people do notice
when they put the thyroid in is they go
oh now doing that cardio and abs at the
end of my workout it doesn't feel like a
chore anymore I kind of look forward to
it now I kind of want to go to the gym
for as long as I can rather than leave
as early as possible now all of a sudden
when I go for a walk it doesn't Fe I'm
not always checking to make sure I've
been going for long enough I just want
to keep going because it feels good to
move and be alive that's true and I like
to say to people that again going back
to the car thing if you were a a car
that had an engine that's too small for
the vehicle which is what hypothyroidism
is you can still go down to the shops to
get milk and bread you can still get
from A to B but it's going to feel
terrible to drive but if you've got a
sports car with a souped up engine and
it feels really good to drive it not
only is that experience going to be
better but you're more likely going to
go for a joy ride so in your spare time
you're more likely going to go and
exercise and get off the couch and
actually go and do the things that you
need to do to achieve your goals and
that's what I love about thyroids so
much it's that it's it's giving people
the energy that they need to put the
testosterone and the other hormones to
use right and hypo and the other thing
that you know we haven't spoken about
this before I recently did a lecture on
I maybe this term exists I coined it
subclinical Hashimoto and this is where
people have got elevated Hashimoto
enzymes that are not above range but
they've got symptoms of hypothyroidism
even when their thyroid panel looks okay
and these people benefit immensely and
these are often the guys who are they're
incomplete from their trt alone and
they're 25 26 years old and they benefit
from just boosting the thyroid up even
if it's only 30 to 60 milligrams of NDT
they do wonderfully with it so it's so
important that people even if you're if
you're just going into this and you're
wanting to look at your hormones get a
comprehensive thyroid panel and look at
your symptoms and don't overlook it and
go oh I've got a little bit of Hashim
Moto now but let's wait until I put on
another 20 kilos of body fat and become
insulin resistant before I fix the
hypothyroidism it's nonsense as as we
said before the wheels are going to fly
off so service it now or or even better
yet Dave I only need testosteron but
testosterone levels are normal but
they're not optimal they're on the low
normal and my thyroids are totally
normal they're they're normal they're
but your thyroids no more optimal than
your testosterone fact when you really
look at it your free T3 is almost tanked
it looks worse than your testosterone
does once again men can buy into
testosterone and start it with normal
levels and realize that hey I can still
be symptomatic with normal levels of
testosterone benefit from testosterone
they have a hard time applying that to
thyroid okay and so when Dave mentions
NDT he's talking about natural
desiccated thyroid and when we talk
about T4 only that's a synthetic T4 and
it's T4 only desicated thyroid is a
mixture of T3 and T4 it's 38 micrograms
of T4 to 9 micrograms of T3 so you're
getting both the problem with taking T4
by itself for me many people as Dave has
alluded to is that T4 is not the active
component of thyroid it's free T3 T4 has
to be converted at the cellular level to
exert the benefits of thyroid and for
those people that take T4 you're going
to kind of decrease your own thyroids
production of T3 and T4 thyroid produces
just for lack of argument sake 75% T4
25% T3 so your thyroid typically is
going to produce both but 75% T4 25% T3
when you take T4 by itself you're going
to shut down that production
of T3 okay and what will happen if
you're not converting your T4 adequately
at the cellular level you become very
you may feel worse because now you have
no T3 and you're not converting
adequately when we take desiccated
thyroid we're taking both T4 and T3 so
you know we're getting our T4 to be
converted and we're also getting our T3
along with it so that we're never kind
of devoid of T3 so those are the
different strens of those two the
problem that the family physician has
with it is that when they see us raise
thyroid levels when you take thyroid
what's going to happen is when you look
at your thyroid panel there's something
called a TSH thyroid stimulating hormone
that's basically your little thermostat
the bigger that number that's your body
saying I need more thyroid the lower
that number is your body saying I don't
need to produce any I do not need to
tell my body to produce any more thyroid
because I've got enough pre T3 will go
up when you take desicated thyroid now
when you take T4 that may not always
happen as Dave's alluded to but that's
the goal is to increase free T3 that's
really what we're looking at
so so when you take it what's going to
happen to your labs when you take
thyroid is when somebody just looks at
those laes they're going to think you're
hyper thyroid it makes you look like
you've got
hyperthyroidism now hyperthyroidism is
Graves disease at Baseline they have a
low TSH they have a high 3 T3 high T4 so
they have a lot of thyroid hormone but
here's the issue Graves disease has an
is an autoimmune disease it's has
autoimmune component that does the
damage yes it causes cardiac abental
like aib and other issues but the
literature is very clear on this taking
thyroid in somebody that is hypothyroid
or subclinically has subclinically
Hashimoto or subclinical hypothyroidism
when they take thyroid and their Labs
move as we said TSH goes down T3 goes up
it does not cause the same squella as
having Graves disease or hyperthyroidism
it does not cause those adverse effects
because there's no autoimmune component
and there's plenty of data out there uh
to to show you that there's some great
PE Papers written by Tomas Kelly on this
very topic and so what I he's even
written a book on it so I'd recommend
that you know but the family doctors we
were taught I was taught that when you
take thyroid you're going to cause
somebody to be hyperthyroid now when you
take thyroid yes is it going to increase
your heart rate a little bit Yeah is it
going to make you feel warmer Dave's
already alluded to that it increases
thermogenesis it increases your
metabolism yes you're going to feel
warmer yes it's going to increase your
heart rate there's no harm in that
whatsoever but if you're one of those
individuals that's extremely sensitive
to it and you feel like you have an
excessive heart rate or feel like you're
having palpitations and or you're having
excessive sweating or heat intolerance
you can simply just lower your dose to
resolve those symptoms once again it's
always a balancing act between raising
levels to resolve symptoms and avoiding
any unwanted side effects and sometimes
it's just lowering the dose and and
finding that that Midway point for you
so anything you want to add to that
there Dave exactly what you said about
the TSH being a signal for the body
wanting more thyroid so I like to use
the analogy usually I have a glass in
front of me but now I've just got the
bottle so it's kind of like if you're in
a restaurant basically the the glass of
water you have is like the T3 and then
this bottle is you signaling to the
waiter to say hey give me more water
that's the TSH so what you want is you
want a full glass and you want you to
shut up and that means that TSH is
generally under one close to to 0.5 if
not lower under one and people think oh
that's great no when you see people who
are 23 24 who are athletes with optimal
thyroid function they generally have a
TSH of like 0.4 0.5 and they have a T3
often above the reference range and I
tell them I go this is rare this is
optimal and this is what we aim for with
hormone replacement now you find me a
50-year-old who's got a natural thyroid
panel looking like that and I tell you
you found Bigfoot it's they didn't exist
um it would just it would especially if
they low testosterone as well be very
unlikely so when it comes to the thyroid
if that TSH is elevated to varying
degrees your body is signaling that it
wants more T3 at the receptor level and
the problem is that there's a whole
bunch of chronic inflammatory conditions
such as insulin resistance which is this
vicious cycle right because insulin
resistance reduces thyroid function
which slows your metabolism which makes
it worse the body gets stuck in these
Vicious Cycles and this is where this
Interventional you know hormone
replacement therapy can break these
Cycles so that people can get their
health back which is why it's such a
cool topic but if your body is signaling
that it needs more TSH so needs more T3
at the receptor level that means that
your metabolism is suboptimal and if
your metabolism is suboptimal it feels
better to have an optimal metabolism you
have more energy to do the things that
you need to do to look after yourself
better people make bad decisions when
they're stressed because they go for the
easy path so that the vast majority of
people even the vast majority majority
of guys under 30 maybe not so much for
maybe if we're talking over 50 it would
be 99% of guys would benefit from
thyroid in terms of under 30 I would
still say 60 to 70% of guys would
benefit from at least some thyroid you
do see the optimal guys every now and
then but you see a couple of them a week
the vast majority of younger guys you
see a bit of an elevation in TSH and it
just might mean that they could benefit
from a little bit of thyroid but the
cool thing about thyroid which you know
you've spoken about before is that yes
this TSH feedback loop is active but
we've got a lot of research to show that
people can withdraw thyroid medication
after years and their natural production
comes right back you die for didn't I
mean basically yeah yeah exactly and
that that's the other thing as well when
it comes to this Graves and hypothyroid
thing is that like yeah so when when
someone has Graves disease it's got that
autoimmune component it just means that
the weight is there just pouring that
water nonstop that feedback loop is gone
and that's why it's so dangerous if you
take a little bit too much thyroid your
body's natural production will just
compensate by lowering but I don't know
about you but I have never found that
someone continues to take medication
that makes them hyperthyroid it's like
coffee there's a certain amount of
coffee that you drink in a day and you
go I'm not going to have anymore if your
dose of thyroid is too high you'll stop
taking it before you end up in hospital
exactly well you've given a lot of
Pearls of Wisdom let's back up to some
really excellent point that you made is
that look these young athletes that have
beautiful thyroid panels every one needs
to understand that our normal range for
thyroid is not for a group of healthy
people it's the average of the
population that you see around you a lot
of times it's made from a captive
population such as those in hospitals or
clinics so the point is is that when a
man says well look my my freet T3 is
normal it's it's 2.6 well the normal
range is 2.2 to 4.4 in some Labs you
know and I'm like but okay it's
2.6 which is at the bottom of the normal
range for a group of sick people is that
where you really want to be so if Dave
and I were to be able to take these
athletes that he's speaking of and just
get our normal ranges from them it would
be a much different normal range and
that's what people need to understand
they they people don't want doctors
paying attention to to labs and normal
but they themselves can't break away
from looking at Labs themselves if you
know what I mean it's kind of a catch 22
for them they'll uh once again they can
understand testosterone to some degree
but but when it comes to the other
hormones they just can't seem to to make
that next step to understand that it's
just like treating testosterone when
we're treating thyroid it's just like
testosterone we're treating really free
testosterone levels and for thyroid it's
about those free T3 levels and yes a
suppressed TSH has never caused harm you
know it's the free T3 level that
correlates best with clinical
Improvement not TSH level my TSH for
instance Dave last time it was tested is
0.7 and you'll see many people with a
suppressed TSA they feel great they feel
wonderful so so the takeaways here is
the normal range is not for healthy
people you know if we got them from the
athletes like they said we we'd have a
much different range and that that's the
key there and following freet T3 and the
fact that taking thyroid will not cause
you to have hyperthyroidism or Graves
disease okay you can have symptoms of
too much just like you can with
testosterone you lower the dose remember
and I try to point this out to people
all the time thyroids been used for over
hundred years I think the first use of
was in the UK around 1891 they used
desiccated thyroid there were no thyroid
lives up until the 1970s just like there
were no testost Labs until the 1970s and
testosterone was first used in 1935 the
mid 1930s so for decades upon decades
upon decades we have been treating men
with testosterone thyroid with no lapse
and it caused no
harm think about that for a minute they
literally treated their symptoms if they
had symptoms of too much they lowered
the dose symptoms too little they raised
the dose that that was a better way to
treat now clinicians for efficiency will
just look at a piece of paper literally
ignore the symptoms or give you a
medication for those symptoms and say
you don't need it because your levels
are normal nothing could be further from
the truth with hormones that's not how
hormones work oh I I couldn't agree more
and you'll get a kick out of this so in
Australia if you and and we talk about
the importance of so in Australia we
have something called um like Medicare
which is like the government subsidized
health program so if if if you as a
doctor order a thyroid panel for TSH T3
and T4 right and you specify that you
want that if TSH comes back below
4.5 they won't run T3 T4 they'll say no
your thyroid is normal and that it
drivve me up one we just get it all done
privately because it's not expensive and
you have to get private care these days
to get good care but the amount of
people who are walking into their
doctor's office with hypothyroid
symptoms who are getting diagnosed with
chronic fatigue syndrome um adrenal
fatigue or just depression and anxiety
would be
astronomical um and they're just it's
just going undetected or even when the
doctor does get a a subclinical hypo lab
back that's obviously that they they'll
go oh it's within range you're just
depressed here's your SSRI right that's
exactly how it works that's exactly how
it works and people need to understand
why has it become so lab Centric because
in order to really treat people like we
do you know you have to sit down with
them and you talk to them and it's going
to take longer than six or 10 minutes
which is the average follow-up time in
America of a family doctor to see
someone you know it's just more
efficient for them to look at a piece of
paper see that it's normal tell you they
don't need it and then just go write a
script for the symptoms that you're
having if just the way the medical
system is set up okay it's just it's not
optimal in any way shape or form we all
know that I never would believe i' would
be talking about this you know 20 years
ago when I was a good little soldier in
that system but now I understand that
the
shortcomings